Okay so today's דף daf is ל״ב Lamed Bet on the fourth
פרק perek of תמיד Tamid and we pick up with about 10
lines from the bottom of ל״א Lamed Aleph ל״ב Lamed Bet מנא
הני מילי mina hanei mili שחר היה נשחט על קרן מזרחית צפונית.
shachar haya nishchat al keren mizrachit tzfoni. So this is talking about
which rings they would שחט shecht the animal on and just to
mention two things directly related number one is I already mentioned yesterday
that רמב״ם Rambam understands that they would not actually bind the leg
and foot together when it says they wouldn't bind it means they
wouldn't bind at all and what they would do is they would
stick the leg and foot when it says they were together through
the ring to hold it steady but almost everybody else disagrees and
says no that they wouldn't bind the front legs by themselves and
the back legs by themselves or all four together but they would
bind the front leg and the front foot together on the left
and then the same on the right and at
least bind and then they put it on those hooks and then
flay.
Yeah when it's time to flay yes but the whole point is
that they want to keep it steady when they שחט shecht it
so it's not moving around and then they would put the head
through the holes. Now the hole they would put it on we
still have the picture
and there's a little confusion because most of the מפרשים mefarshim say
that it was this ring it was the second ring that it
said like in the morning it said it would be
on the you know in the northwest and in the and in
the afternoon
in the north שחר shachar was the northeast שחר היה נשחט על
קרן מזרחית צפונית shachar haya nishchat al keren mizrachit tzfoni שחר מזרחית
צפונית shachar mizrachit tzfoni
and yes
that's definitely that's definitely the opening hold
on hold on hold on oh my goodness give me a hard
time
שחר קרן צפונית מערבית shachar keren tzfoni ma'aravit so yeah the text
you're quoting wrong look at the look at the bottom.
Anyway so it says northwest in the morning and northeast in the
afternoon probably at this is North right this is North so most
of the מפרשים mefarshim say right this is North this is South
most of the מפרשים mefarshim say that North means the northeast relative
to the northeast corner of the מזבח mizbe'ach and when it says
northwest it means the northwest corner of the מזבח mizbe'ach it's not
the north of the entire space but I should mention that the
יכין ובועז Yachin Boaz the תפארת ישראל Tiferet Yisrael the classic commentary
on the משנה mishnah said and he says that the רמב״ם Rambam
agrees with him it sounds like the רמב״ם Rambam agrees that northeast
and northwest means not north close to the northeast and northwest corner
of the מזבח mizbe'ach but northeast and northwest of the entire space
right so this is the north and they would be on this.
So anyway there's a question it would be on the second ring
would it be the second ring here from you know second ring
column from this end or would it be two columns from the
other end.
But anyway it would be on the second ring and the question
is why is the morning one in the west and the afternoon
one in the east? So let's take a look at the גמרא
gemara מנא הני מילי mina hanei mili where's this from? אמר רב
חסדא אמר קרא amar Rav Chisda amar kra the פסוק pasuk says
שנים ליום shnayim layom two a day by the תמיד Tamid כנגד
היום kineged hayom facing the sun יום yom meaning here the sun
תניא
נמי הכי tanya nami hachi we taught similarly שנים ליום כנגד היום
shnayim layom kineged hayom אתה אומר כנגד היום ata omer kineged hayom
facing the sun או אינו אלא חובת היום o eino ela chovat
hayom maybe it means that you know two is your daily obligation
which is פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. No כשהוא אומר את
הכבש האחד תעשה בבקר ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים keshehu omer
et hakeves ha'echad ta'aseh baboker ve'et hakeves hasheni ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim one
lamb in the morning and one in the afternoon so it's pretty
explicit הרי חובת היום אמור harei chovat hayom amur I know you
bring two you know your daily obligation is two. המני מקיים שנים
ליום hamani mekayem shnayim layom
why does it then again say two each day? That's pretty obvious.
So to tell you כנגד היום kineged hayom facing the sun
הכיצד ha'keitzad how do you do this? תמיד של שחר היה נשחט
על קרן צפונית מערבית Tamid shel shachar haya nishchat al keren tzfoni
ma'aravit the morning one was on the northwest corner again northwest meaning
near the northwest corner of the מזבח mizbe'ach על טבעת שניה al
taba'at shniya on the second on the second ring. So does that
mean near the northwest corner of the מזבח mizbe'ach or does it
mean like I said the רמב״ם Rambam suggests or sounds like in
the רמב״ם Rambam the northwest of the entire space which so you
know it would be the further row. But anyway on the northwest
corner ושל בין הערבים היה נשחט על קרן צפונית מזרחית veshel bein
ha'arbayim haya nishchat al keren tzfoni mizrachit and the afternoon one would
be on the northeast על טבעת שניה al taba'at shniya on the
second ring.
So the reason here you're doing this is because the sun is
rising here the shadows right there are walls you know there's a
wall here and there's a wall here so shadows are like being
cast.
So if you want it facing the sun you get it here
right the wall is here that's further away from the shadow and
similarly at sunset right you're getting the shadows being cast in the
opposite direction so in order
to have it directly in the sunlight you want it here at
the opposite end so in the morning you want it in the
west and in the evening you want it in the east.
Okay that's the idea in order to get it facing the sun.
Michael of course makes a good point you would think דוקא davka
you don't want it to be sort of seem like sun worship
so you might have like specifically avoided that. I don't know what
to say about that occurred to me as well. Now we move
on to a fascinating אגדתא aggadata and you can try to sort
of figure out what it's doing here but this is an extended
אגדתא aggadata let's take a look. Yeah, go ahead.
I was just reviewing the משנה mishnah *Mishna*, was just like, you
know, sort of saying
that there was a process and then filling in some more of
the details because they were talking about
that... you gave the ראש Rosh *Rosh*, and then you gave it
to whoever was זוכה *zoche*, but then later on it talks about
putting the fat on. Right. So, but that's after a couple of
other steps. Yeah. Like did it... what do you mean? We already
gave it to somebody. How are you putting it...
You're standing here. I'm giving you the head. Now I'm getting up
to the fat. Now it takes time because I can't get to
the fat right away. I've got an order I have to do
when I'm cutting it apart. Then I finally get to the fat.
I say, Michael, come over here, or maybe you're standing right next
to me and I put the fat together with your head. So,
but you can't cut it up in the order in which the
people are carrying it because, you know, you have to cut it
up in an order that's dictated by the reality of how do
you dismember an animal. Okay, so but it is true the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* completely ignores the משנה mishna *Mishna*. Totally.
Just another point, that, you know, we were talking about our bottom
area where the feet is later on. Yes. Because I was wondering
about that, you know, when we were saying it didn't seem like
it was, but they just have a note over here, they're saying
that actually ראב"ד *Ra'avad* said that first they flay the feet.
Who says?
They said the ראב"ד *Ra'avad* says that.
Okay, so it doesn't sound like it's from the משנה mishnah *Mishna*,
could be. Okay, I did want to point out though, because you
mentioned the feet, that that bit was interesting. It says that who
carried... you know they chopped off right at the bottom with the
hooves and they put that together with... with the intestines. Right? That
was the last guy. So it's like why are the feet together
with the intestines? So I was, you know, okay they're both dirty-ish.
So anyway I was reading the רמב"ם *Rambam* and I realized he
quoted a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. You know what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
is? והקרב והכרעים ירחץ במים *ve-ha-kerev ve-ha-kera'ayim yirchatz ba-mayim*. Every day, I
read that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, it never occurred to me, right? It
means the innards and the feet. Why דווקא *davka* the feet? So
what it means is you dismember, you cut off the feet, the
hoof area separately, and that's the dirty part, and you wash them
all together. So it's ממש *mamash* in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that
the feet are cut off separately and then are treated together with
the... with the innards, and they're brought together and here we see
that they're carried together. So it actually just struck me that that's
why you're giving the feet to that guy.
Okay, so let's take a look
now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
It's funny that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't quote that פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*.
I know.
Yeah, I understand that, that's why I'm sharing it with you. But
yeah.
Okay so let's take... the רמב"ם *Rambam* also didn't quote it to
say it's why the same person. He was just describing the process
of how you would prepare it and he said you would ורחץ
את הקרב והכרעים *ve-rochatz et ha-kerev ve-ha-kera'ayim*. So it's like, oh yeah,
that's the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. Anyway, okay, so moving on. עשרה דברים
שאל אלכסנדרוס מוקדון את זקני הנגב *asara devarim she'al Alexandros Mokdon et
ziknei ha-Negev*. Ten things Alexander the Great, Alexander of Macedon, that's מוקדון
*Mokdon*, Alexander the Great, asked the elders of the South. אמר להן
amar lahen, *amar la-hen*, he said to them, you know, שמים וארץ
*shamayim va-aretz* top of ל"ב עמוד א' Lamed Bet Amud Alef. *lamed
bet amud aleph*. מן שמים לארץ רחוק או ממזרח למערב *min shamayim
la-aretz rachok o mi-mizrach le-ma'arav*. Which is long... which is a further
distance, from earth to the sky or from the east to the
west? Okay. אמרו לו amru lo, *amru lo*, they said to him,
ממזרח למערב *mi-mizrach le-ma'arav*, from the east to the west. Why? תדע
*teda*, this is presumably why it's quoted, because we spoke about the
east, the sun rising in the east and shining into the west,
we mentioned the sun rising east and west and here it's about
the sun in the east and the west. So, חמה במזרח הכל
מסתכלין בה *chama be-mizrach ha-kol mistaklin bah*, the sun is in the
east, everyone can look at it during sunrise. Okay. חמה במערב הכל
מסתכלין בה *chama be-ma'arav ha-kol mistaklin bah*, sunset, it's in the west,
everyone can look at it. חמה באמצע רקיע rakia, אין הכל מסתכלין
בה *chama be-emtza raki'a ein ha-kol mistaklin bah*, at noon in the
middle of the sky when it's directly overhead, not everyone can look
at it, you can't look at it. Try to look directly at
the sun when it's overhead. So why is that? It must be
that it's closer to the earth when it's directly overhead because it's
closer it hurts your eyes and it's further away when it's in
the east and the west. Now that's of course not true and
let's see upon reading in the גמרא Gemorah? *Gemara*, I mean, you
know, it's like a circle obviously, anyway the earth is just rotating.
But anyway, it's not about it being further, let's keep on reading.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tells like this: וחכמים אומרים *ve-chachamim omrim*. Now
this is obviously an insertion in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, however the
Sages say, or I don't know, it seems like an insertion, maybe
it's part of the original story, זה וזה כאחד שוין *zeh va-zeh
ke-echad shavin*, they're actually the same, the distance from heaven and earth
as it is from east to west. שנאמר shenemar, *shene'emar*, as the
verse says, כגבוה שמים על הארץ *ki-gevo'ah shamayim al ha-aretz*, like the
height of the heavens over the earth, and then it keeps on
going and describes כרחוק מזרח ממערב *ki-rachok mizrach mi-ma'arav*, the distance from
the east to the west. So it compares something both to the,
you know, the height of... these two distances are being used in
the same metaphor. ואי חד מינייהו נפיש *ve-i chad mineihu nafish*, and
if one of them was a greater distance, אמאי נכתוב תרווייהו
*amai nichtov travaihu*? Why have to write both of them? כי האי
דנפיש *ki hai de-nafish*, just write the longer one, right? If you're
going to compare it, why compare it to two distances? You should
just compare it to the larger one. So why does it use
both metaphors? So must be that they are equal, that the distance
is the same. So then the גמרא *Gemara* says, if that's true,
what about the proof that they brought about not being able to
look at the sun? ואלא חמה באמצע רקיע rakia. מאי טעמא אין
הכל מסתכלין בה *ve-ela chama be-emtza raki'a mai ta'ama ein ha-kol mistaklin
bah*. So why can't you look at the sun directly, why does
it appear brighter at midday? משום דקאי להדיא *meshum de-kai le-hedya*, because
it's directly overhead, ולא כסי ליה מידי *ve-lo kasi lei midi*, and
nothing covers it up. So what does that mean, what covers it
up when it's over here? So the מפרשים meforshim *meforshim* say, well...
You know the sun rays have to go through all the geography
that's between you and the sun, so you know mountains and other
types of things, so that's you know diffracting some of the some
of the brightness or whatever, minimizing some of the brightness as opposed
to it's directly overhead, nothing is there, nothing is in the way.
So I actually said, hmm, what is the answer to that? I
didn't know the answer, so if Charlie was here he would tell
us the answer. Does anybody know why is the sun just brighter
when it's overhead?
It has to go through more atmosphere.
So it's atmosphere. It is similar, it is, it has to go
through more atmosphere. But what does that mean more? Doesn't make sense.
But explain more atmosphere, I mean if you've got a dome, right,
why is it more atmosphere? So I asked my student, I think
it anyway has to do with the angle of the refraction.
Ah, so that anyway I looked it up on the web. I
was, wanted more atmosphere, I was trying to figure out what that
meant, which anyway sounds like this answer anyway. One of my students
explained it to me, he drew a picture here.
Oh, it's like this. So if you've got the sun directly overhead,
for every square
unit of light, right, it goes sort of directly down, right? But
if the sun is sort of, if you're here, right, you have
the sun, it's sort of, the sun is rising here. So apparently,
I'm not sure exactly, something like the idea that the direct light
hits, hits at like an angle, right? Because the sun is sort
of like at an angle, the direct light sort of, the full
unit of light hits at the angle, and then from that to
get down to me sort of gets stretched so that the, that
same unit of light gets stretched over more, more space because it's
not hitting me directly, it's hitting me at an angle and then
the same sort of unit of light is stretched.
Is that what you'd say Michael, by refracted?
Refraction is also why when
like the moon is on the horizon.
That's more or less what you were saying, right? So that's the
way I understand it.
I think it's related also to why when like the moon is
on the horizon it can sometimes look very large, much larger, and
then as it goes up it, it, it looks smaller, but I
think it's related to that.
Okay. So anyway, but certainly, anyway, no,
the reason why the moon is on an horizon looks larger is
because you need more things to see it relative to where you
are, so it looks bigger when you compare it to the
size of the moon, sorry, the surface of the moon.
I don't know. Alright.
So, so we're equally,
I'm filling in for Charlie but so
we're equally stumped as the זקני נגב here.
And they thought the sky has like a ceiling, you know.
Yes, correct. And a back. I understand. But, but that still wouldn't
explain if you had a dome, right? So then, and you're the
center of the dome, you have the radius, your space still, I
mean if you feel that it was a perfectly circular dome. But
they didn't think so. I think they did. They, no, they think
the, the sun went underneath the dome, right, and then in the
evening it went on top of the dome and came out the
next morning. I think that anyway. Alright, so that was their answer.
Their answer was from east to west. I was trying to interpret
this in more metaphoric terms, although as you'll see in the end
I don't think the גמרא means it metaphorically because there's other, there's
a parallel to this whole story. But anyway, you know, I was
trying to think about it like, like, you know, who's closer, people
that are like are opposite of one another in the, you know
what they say like opposites attract, you know? Or like Rav Kook,
I was thinking about Rav Kook's point that he thinks like, he,
he feels that like the, the atheist is closer to the believer
than the agnostic because he's like really passionate about his belief in
what he so what he doesn't believe in or what he's rejecting,
but still there's this sense of this search for truth and so
on. So, you know, I was sort of thinking about the closeness
of high to low, of like opposites as opposed to things that
are just at different points on a spectrum, you know, that maybe
in some ironic way things that are opposite are even closer than
things that are just distant on a spectrum. I don't know, but
anyway, it's not exactly clear that this was meant metaphorically although you'd
like to interpret it that way. Let's keep on reading. So the
גמרא says like this. Okay. אמר להן, amar lahen, he said to
them, שמים נבראו תחלה או ארץ, shamayim nivru techila o aretz,
was the heavens created first or the land? This actually is מחלוקת
machlokes בית שמאי בית הלל Beis Shammai Beis Hillel in the בראשית
רבה. Bereishis Rabbah. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says the heavens were created
first: בראשית ברא אלקים את השמים ואת הארץ, bereishis bara elohim es
hashamayim ve'es ha'aretz, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says the land was
created first, which also reflects their basic orientation towards like you know
God and הלכה halacha and everything, whether you focus fundamentally on humans
and their reality or fundamentally on the heavens and God and so
on. Anyway, so that's what he asked them, which was created first,
heaven or earth? אמרו, amru, they said, שמים נבראו תחלה, shamayim nivru
techila, heaven, שנאמר, Shene'emar, בראשית ברא אלקים את השמים ואת הארץ. bereishis
bara elohim es hashamayim ve'es ha'aretz. So what did they say? I
don't, so you look at the בראשית רבה, Bereishis Rabbah, they quote
a different פסוק. אמר להן, amar lahen, so he said to them,
okay, אור נברא תחלה או חשך, or nivra techila o choshech, light,
was light created first or darkness? אמרו amru, לו, they said to
him, מלתא דא אין לה פתר, milta da ein lah petar, ah,
there's no answer to that question. So now the גמרא says, לנימרו
ליה חשך נברא תחלה, lenimru leh choshech nivra techila, I don't get
it, say darkness because the פסוק says, והארץ היתה תהו ובהו וחשך,
veha'aretz hayesa tohu vavohu vechoshech, the land was you know void and,
and there was darkness, והדר, vehadar, and afterwards, ויאמר אלקים יהי אור
ויהי אור, vayomer elohim yehi or vayehi or, God said let there
be light. סברי, savri, no they thought, דלמא אתי לשיולינהו, dilma asi
leshiyuleina, now we're starting you know, oh, well was heaven and earth
and light and darkness, now he's going to start asking us מה
למעלה מה למטה מה לפנים מה לאחור, mah lema'ala mah lemata mah
lefanim mah leachor, the famous משנה in חגיגה. Chagigah. He's going to
ask us all the secrets of the universe and maybe we don't
know, or maybe even if we know we don't want to tell
him. So he's going to ask us what's really above, what's deep,
what's below, what's before the world, what's before and after, some say
it means chronologically before the world was created, what will be after
the world starts, stops existing, or maybe it means, you know, what
exists like,
you know, outside of the, outside of the universe. לפנים lifnim so
like no that's a question like what's outside of the universe? So
nothing. Anyway, but okay, and what's so what's in front, what's behind,
אי הכי ei hachi so someone said if they don't want to
get into these sort of cosmological, theological discussions, אי הכי שמיא נמי
לא נימרו ליה ei hachi shamaya nami lo nimru lei don't answer
him when he asks about the heaven and earth. Someone says
no, מעיקרא סבר אקראי בעלמא הוא דקשייל me'ikara savar akrai b'alma hu
d'kasha'il for they thought okay, it's one question, he's asking heaven and
earth, we'll give an answer. כיוון דחזא דקהדר שייל keivan d'chaza d'kahadar
sha'yel then he says oh my god he's sticking on this topic
and he's starting to talk about other things, light and darkness, סברי
לא נימרה ליה savri lo nimrah lei let's not give an answer.
דילמא אתי לשאולנו dilma atei lish'alenu
because he's going to come to ask us once we start giving
him answers about this stuff מה למעלה מה למטה מה לפנים מה
לאחור ma l'ma'ala ma l'mata ma l'fanim ma l'achor so we have
to like shut it down now. Sorry, no more answers on this
topic.
It was interesting for a second there, I was like oh well,
I was like this is the first time I've ever seen them
not have an answer to something, then realized it was a strategy.
Right. The interesting question about light and darkness is also there's different
commentators about did God create darkness or is darkness just the absence
of light and it's not a created idea, which gets into like
important theological questions about like does evil come from God or is
evil the absence of God's presence, you know? The פסוק we say
every morning is, you know, יוצר אור ובורא חושך yotzer or u'vorei
choshech but the end of the פסוק is עושה שלום ובורא רע
oseh shalom u'vorei ra and we switch it to ובורא את הכל
u'vorei et hakol so, you know, the interesting thing is about that,
so that also could be part of what's going on here about
you don't want to get into a discussion which was created first
because do you really want to speak about darkness as something created
or as the absence of light? Okay. So why didn't they want
him to know?
Let's assuming they knew. Right.
Why didn't they want him to know? Why didn't they share the
answer? I don't know, I mean that gets into the question about
why you're not supposed to share מעשה בראשית ma'aseh bereishis in general,
right? I mean the whole משנה in חגיגה Chagigah that it's like
these secrets. No, it's חגיגה Chagigah about the אין דורשין בשנים ein
dorshin b'shnayim אין דורשין בשנים ein dorshin b'shnayim and so on. Anyway,
I mean so you know it gets into this whole concept of
esoteric knowledge and that esoteric knowledge can't be trusted in the hands
of. He was asking them though.
He was asking.
I understand, but you know everybody that asks you the secret esoteric
knowledge are you going to divulge? I mean it gets into the
general question of what was the whole idea of this esoteric knowledge.
What? Did it give them certain powers which would lead, you know,
was there a sense, we don't have as much of a sense
nowadays as there of like, you know, forbidden knowledge. I actually had
a book once, I haven't read it, but it actually was called
Forbidden Knowledge, you know, it had the picture of Adam and Eve
in the garden of Eden and like, you know, the עץ eitz
and the tree of knowledge. So, you know, there's this, but you
know or like Jack Nicholson in A Few Good Men, you can't
handle the truth.
So very often women were excluded from.
Right, that's a good point. Right, I mean that is true, knowledge
and who gets certain knowledge is very much about power and control.
So that's certainly true. But it's a broader question in חגיגה Chagigah
about this issue. There's danger regarding some of this stuff as well,
right?
Right, right. Oh, you mean so danger not just to
yourself as well that somehow this knowledge, right, destructive. Yeah. So I
think that's definitely a part of it, that this knowledge gives you
power or is maybe something that can hurt you or others. So
anyways, it's not clear whether they, right, whether they had the answers
and didn't want to get into the discussion or didn't want to.
It sounds like, it does sound like that they didn't want to
get into the, not like they didn't know but they didn't want
to get into the discussion. Okay, so now he asks other questions.
Ha, the next questions are softball questions. אמר להם amar lahem he
said to them אידין מתקרי חכם idin mitkari chacham who's called a
wise person? אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him איזהו חכם
הרואה את הנולד eizehu chacham haroeh et hanolad this is oh, that's
easy, that's פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. Okay. Who's the wise person? The
one who sees the future. אמר להם amar lahem he said to
them אידין מתקרי גיבור idin mitkari gibor who's considered, you know, valorous,
mighty? אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him איזהו גיבור הכובש
את יצרו eizehu gibor hakovesh et yitzro who is courageous or mighty,
the person who conquers his own inclination. אמר להם amar lahem he
said to them אידין מתקרי עשיר idin mitkari ashir who is called
wealthy? אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him איזהו עשיר השמח
בחלקו eizehu ashir hasamei'ach bechelko the one who is happy in his
lot. אמר להם amar lahem מה יעביד איניש ויחיה ma ya'avid inish
v'yichyeh what should a person do and live? אמרו ליה amru lei
they said to him ימית עצמו yamit atzmo let him kill himself.
Now, what does that mean? So it could mean sort of deny
himself physical and bodily pleasures, you know, live a spiritual life. It
could mean like, you know, modest, right? Maybe.
It could mean, so what I immediately
associated with it is זאת התורה אדם כי ימות באוהל zot hatorah
adam ki yamut b'ohel the מדרש midrash that says, you know, אין
התורה מתקיימת... ein hatorah mitkayemet... מתקיימת אלא במי שממית עצמו עליה. mitkayemet
ela bemi shemeimit atmo aleha. That the תורה Torah is established with
somebody who kills himself over it, which means you abandon all things
and it's self-sacrifice for the sake of תורה. Torah. And the מפרשים
mefarshim say one or the other, like the ראש Rosh says, either
it means the ראש also says it means get a good honest
job and work hard at your job. He says, or deny, don't
indulge in pleasures, or self-sacrifice for תורה Torah and for religious pursuit.
So what's interesting is when they asked him who's, when he asked
them, I should say, who's a smart one? They didn't say whoever
knows the most תורה. Torah. They just said רואה את
הנולד,
roeh
et
hanolad, and I understand the משנה in אבות, Avos, but that's true.
I want to get back to the whole thing about what is
the, I think the subtext of this.
So let's just finish the questions, okay? It could also just be
reducing your ego, kills yourself. Yeah, that's I think similar, I don't
know if that's what Michael was high-driving at.
Yeah, like self-abnegation, right, exactly.
And I want to get back to all this because there's a
theme here. מה יעביד איניש וימות? ma yaavid inish veyamut? What should
a person do that will lead to death? יחיה את עצמו. yechaye
et atmo. Give yourself life, which means basically the opposite. Indulge in
physical pleasures, take the easy life, don't have a life of self-sacrifice,
blow yourself up in terms of your ego, all of those things.
אמר להן, amar lahen, מה יעביד איניש ויתקבל על הבריות? ma yaavid
inish veyitkabel al habriut? What should a person do to be accepted,
to be sort of find favor by the people על הבריות, al
habriyos, on God's creations? But that people will like him. טוב אמרו,
tov amru, so הם אמרו, amru, על הבריות, al habriyosa, excuse me,
on people, אמרו, they said, ישנא מלכות ושלטון. yisne malchut veshilton. Let
him despise kingship and rule. So they hated the king. Yeah, it's
a little pointed of a statement. Now some say it means personally
you shouldn't go, don't go into politics. The famous גמרות gemaras about
that. שררה אני נותן לכם? עבדות אני נותן לכם. srara ani noten
lachem? avdut ani noten lachem. Anyway, it completely reminds me of the
famous story, the joke I like to tell, which is somebody is
going to the little שטעטל shtetl to visit his son, and his
son is a גבאי gabbai or the שול shul president. Anyway, let's
say he's the שול shul president. You know where my son חיים,
Chaim, the שול shul president, lives? חיים? Chaim? That good-for-nothing, that liar,
that cheater? Yeah, go down there, three blocks, whatever. Anyway, he gets
lost, he asks somebody else, same story. That turncoat, that sneak, whatever,
he goes this way. Anyway, on and on and on. Finally, he
comes, he finds his son's house, and he says, חיים, Chaim, he
says, tell me, why did you agree to be a שול shul
president? It's a lot of work, long hours, it doesn't pay anything,
why do you do it? He says, Pop, I'll tell you. It's
for the כבוד. kavod. So that's like the, what do you want
to do that you, if you don't want people to be angry
at you, avoid being, avoid positions of authority, that's one thing. Now
the other explanation, obviously, it's a little pointed message to say to
Alexander the Great, which I'll get back to, but the other interpretation
is not that you should avoid authority, but the other point that
comes up in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, which is תרחק מן הרשות,
tisrachak min hareshut, meaning keep your distance from authority. You think you're
going to curry favor with your people by
being an interceder, and there's
obviously was the court Jew, I mean that was a major important
role in the Middle Ages, was to be in that position and
probably those people were very much loved by their community, but here
it is saying, I'm sure there were, sure יש ויש, yesh veyesh,
but anyway, here it is saying, you'll just get same idea, you'll
get everybody angry at you, keep your distance from the government, from
the king. But the more pointed response is don't look for ruler,
don't look for kingship and authority. So then he says, אמר להו,
amar lehu, he said to them, דידי טבא מדידכון, didi tava midichon,
I have a better answer. Not that you should avoid authority, either
you being, having authority or being close to authority, but the opposite.
ירחם מלכות ושלטון, yerachem malchut veshilton, you should desire, love kingship and
authority. Why? Because that'll give you the ability to help people. ומהני
לבני אינשא, vmaheni livnei insha, so that'll help you do good to
people. So therefore it's a good thing to have authority if you
use it properly. אמר להן, amar lahen, he said to them, בימא
יאי למידר? beyama yae lmeida? Is it better to live on the
ocean? או ביבשתא יאי למידר? o beyabeshta yae lmeida? Or on the
dry land? Well, that seems obvious. אמרו ליה, amru leh, they said
to him, ביבשתא יאי למידר. beyabeshta yae lmeida. It's better to live
on dry land. How do you know? דהא כל נחותי ימא, dehachol
nechoseiy yamma, everybody that goes to the sea, the sailors, לא מיתבא
דעתייהו עד דסלקי ליבשתא. lo mitba daitaihu ad desalki leyabeshta. They don't
feel settled until they finally get back to dry land, able to
put their feet back on dry land, so clearly it's better. I
am going to tell you what I think is the overarching פשט
pshat here. Let's finish the questions. אמר להן, Amar lehen, he said
to them, אידי מנכון חכים יתיר? idi minnechon chakim yatir? Which one
of you is the smartest? אמרו ליה, amru leh, they said to
him, כולנו כחדא שווינן. kulanu kechada shamayinan. We're all equally smart. דהא
כל מילתא דאמרת לן כחדא פתחנא לך. dehachol milta deamarta lan bekchad
patanu lach. Anything you said to us... אמר להן, Amar lehen, he
said to them, מה ביני אריסטום לקבלי, Ma beini Aristom l'kabli, why
are you opposing me? What does it mean opposing me? Opposing my
rulership, opposing me? A lot of the מפרשים say it means not
accepting my religion, why are you so insistent on your Jewish religion?
So אמרו ליה, Amru ley, they said to him, סטינא נצח, stitna
natzach, the Satan has won. Now is victorious. Now that was, I
actually checked Soncino, they sometimes have interesting notes, and they say it
here meant it was a double entendre, meaning it could be read
as like, oh, you know, the Satan has gotten the better of
us, and that's why we are not, the יצר הרע's yetzer hara
getting the better of us and that's why we're not following you.
But the real meaning is the Satan's getting the better of you,
or the Satan is victorious in the sense of, I'm sorry, the
Satan is victorious meaning like you, the Satan, or whatever, the Greek,
or whatever, right now you're in the ascendancy, but that doesn't mean
you're right, you're still the evil. So yes, the Satan sometimes wins,
but it doesn't mean they're actually in the right as well. No,
that's why, no, well, that's why the Soncino said it was like
a double entendre. They framed it as if they were saying the
Satan has gotten the better of us. They just said the Satan
sometimes wins. Okay, and yes, they were friends. Well, yes, that's true,
Alexander and the Jews were, right, they were historically friends. Just in
each other's way. Exactly, it is true, yes, so some of these
answers are a little pointed. Anyway, it's true, it's a little dangerous.
אמר להן, amar lahen, he said to them, הנא מכתלינא יתכון בגזירת
מלכין, hana maktalina yathkon begzeirat malkhin, I'm going to kill you all
out by the king's edict. Maybe he got the point that they
were saying some negative things. אמרו ליה, Amru ley, they said to
him, שלטון ביד מלכא, shilton beyad malka, the kingship is in the
hands or control, like kingship is in the hands of the king,
so you have the power or authority maybe is in the hands
of the king. ולא יאה למלכא כדב, v'lo ya'eh l'malka k'dav, and
it's not appropriate for the king to lie. So presumably what does
it mean lie? Presumably he had promised them, maybe he promised as
a precondition for having this discussion that he would not do anything
in reaction to their answers, but clearly there was some promise here
and they said you can't go back
on your promise now if you
don't like our answers and do something to us. מיד אלבשינהו לבושין
דרגון, miyad albishinhu levushin dargavan, so then he sort of
totally reversed himself, you
guys won, so he had to clothe them in cloaks of royal
purple, ושוי מניכא דדהבא על צוריהון, v'shavi manicha d'dahava al tzavreihon, and
put like a golden necklaces on their around their necks. It was
like a combination of Mordechai and Yosef, right? מרדכי יצא בלבוש מלכות,
Mordechai yatza bilvush malchut, for Yosef it was ורביד הזהב על צוארו.
v'ravid hazahav al tzavro. Okay, now we're going to get onto the
next part of the story, but before we get onto the next
part I want to say one or two things about this. First
of all, here's what I think the overarching theme is, and it's
very much borne out in the next story. It is about his
sort of ambition and his desire to be like a world conqueror,
and how the rabbis are responding to that. So first of all,
the very fact that you're thinking like heaven and earth, east and
west, it's sort of like you have this sort of lust for
the entire world, which might also have to be about the idea
of talking about like heaven and earth as opposed to east and
west, because east and west he wanted to conquer the entire civilized
world, well he sort of did, but that's like the east and
the west. So maybe pointing out like that's a very vast amount.
And similar questions about light and darkness and so on, I sort
of see as just symbolic of somebody that has a very vaunting
ambition. But then it comes to no, just the idea like you
have these sort of thoughts about the entire universe. So very large,
obviously they're not petty thoughts, obviously they're these thoughts about the entire,
but I think it doesn't get clear until the next stage. The
next stage I think makes it very clear, because who's wise? Does
anybody know who Alexander's tutor was? Aristotle. Okay. Who's wise? Who is
wealthy? Who is strong? and so on. So he's thinking it's all
about you get taught by Aristotle, you conquer the world, obviously that's
strong, then you have wealth, and they say no, they like sort
of missed the boat. True wisdom is being able to anticipate the
future, and certainly true wealth and true valor is not in terms
of conquering worlds, it's conquering yourself, and איזהו גבור הכובש את יצרו.
eizehu gibbor hakovesh et yitzro. And so, one minute, and conquering and
being satisfied with what you have, not always lusting after more and
desiring more and more. And then clearly the next part, about about.
is brought as of how do you live, how do you die,
right? It's the same type of point. Is it all about amassing
wealth and you know, that? No, that's giving yourself life, but ultimately
it gives you death, as opposed to the more sort of, you
know, self-denial and devoting yourself to more spiritual purposes, that's what true
life is about. And then finally ending with the discussion about authority.
Right? He says, look, I have the better answer. Authority and power
is good, and everybody loves you. And they say, no, authority and
power is something to be avoided. Now that does raise interesting questions.
It's easy for powerless people to say authority and power is something
to be avoided. I mean, there is a lot of responsibility and
a lot of good that can
be done with power and authority.
But obviously, I think that that's clearly sort of the subtext about
all of this is about, you know, his ambition and desire for
more and a very physicality in the land. Ah, so the sea
and the land. I thought what it means is, you know, is
that if you want everything, you don't just, you know, so it's
not good enough you living on land. You want to have a
boat and you want to live on the ocean, you know, and
your desires are so expansive, you're never satisfied. But at the end
of the day, you know, you can't live on the sea. That's
not ultimately where, you know, so like you're trying to conquer the
world and you should learn how to be satisfied with what you
have. It's not necessarily that it's better to, you know, to be
in some foreign place than it is to be at home. And
we're going to see a story, the immediate next story is exactly
that, that he goes to try to conquer these foreign places and
in a way it's sort of like why are you bothering leaving
home? You're looking for satisfaction like out on the sea. You should,
you know, just stay home and be happy with that. What do
you make about which of you is smarter? Ah, so who is
smarter than who? So anyway, I was researching this because I figured
there's got to be some other thing going on here. And I
found, fascinatingly, in the Jewish Encyclopedia, which is now all online, so
that was easy to find. They have a whole section on Alexander
the Great and about the Talmudic legends of Alexander the Great. And
they said that there are parallels to a lot of these legends
in classical literature. So I want to read to you what they
say. But first the classic, well, it's Plutarch. So Plutarch first. Okay,
so here's what they say. It says, this account is written about
the ten questions the sages of the south, I wasn't counting, I
was expecting you to count,
Michael, in classical
Aramaic, providing that it was borrowed from some, proving that it was
borrowed from some written record. It's quite analogous to the conversations which,
according to Plutarch, Alexander was reported to have had with ten Gymnosophists
who had rebelled against him. There the account continues with ten questions,
some of which are identical to the Talmudic narrative. This episode seems
to be a fragment of a non-Jewish narrative parallel with that of
the Greek historians. So if you take a look at the questions,
right? Some, a lot of the questions were, if you hear, like
sentence two, the first one being asked was, I'm sorry, oh so
he said to them the following, he said, declaring in the middle
here of sentence one, that he would put to death him who
first made an incorrect answer, and the rest in an order determined
in like manner. And he would put to death the first one
who said something wrong and then he would keep on putting to
death people that gave wrong answers. Okay, the first one he said,
which are more numerous, the living or the dead? They said, the
living were, since the dead no longer existed. So the dead you
can't count them. The second being asked whether earth or sea produced
larger animals? They said the earth did, since the sea was but
part of the earth. Okay, okay. The third being, which animal was
more cunning? They said that which man has not yet discovered. So
very cunning to stay away forever. The fourth, why they had induced,
why he had induced, it should be they, not he, induced the
Sabbas, oh he, I guess the person he's asking, to revolt? They
replied because I wished him either to live nobly or to die
nobly, basically. The fifth being asked which was older, day or night?
They replied day by one day. And he added upon the king's
expressing amazement that hard questions must have hard answers. What does that
sound like? It's a parallel to our discussion. When he asked him
which came first, light or darkness, and he shut down the question,
right? So here too, he gave him like a trick answer that
didn't make sense and it's about day or night. So that's very
similar. Okay, how could a man be most loved? Okay, if he
is most powerful yet does not inspire fear, right? So as opposed
to the answer of the sages here, which is if he's not
powerful, if he avoids power. Okay, so obviously it's still a point
to Aristotle but here it's still about power as opposed to our
answer which was about avoiding power. Of those present, what might a
man do to become a god? By doing something which man cannot.
Okay, so no surprise, that's not in our text. The one who
asked which was stronger, life or death, said life, since it supports
many ills. Okay, you suffer a lot in life. And the last
he asked how long it were well for a man to live,
until he does not regard death as better than life. That's a
pretty potent answer. So then, turning to the judge, so now they
gave the answers, answer bade... The judge declared that they had answered
one worse than another. They'd all given one the next one the
worst answers, so I don't understand how that gets them out of
being killed. They all gave bad answers according to this. Anyway, well
then, you shall die for giving such a verdict. That cannot be
okay, unless you falsely said you would put to death him who
answered the worst. So I don't exactly get how this riddle here,
whatever, how he avoided it, but what does this echo in our
גמרא? Which of you is smarter? So how do you get out
of it? You say, well, we're all equal, right? So if we're
all equal, maybe you were going to punish the one that was
smarter. So he said no, no, no, we're all equal, so you
can't pick one out more than the other, nobody is smarter, and
then he wants to kill them, and then he says, you promised
not to kill us. So there's obviously a very big echo. It's
interesting to see the differences. Of course, also the difference structurally is
in this story, each one gave a different answer, whereas in our
story they all gave the same answer, which was born out, you
know, emphasized at the end, which maybe has to do with a
concept about unity, you know, and so on, about, you know, that
sort of the answer at the end. Now I have seen that
this was reframed, that this place was apparently in some versions this
place is India, and some people want to understand that these were
the Brahmins, like the Indian sages that were giving these answers. So
here are these sort of different versions of the story, but it
again is interesting to see how it's reworked. But I think as
I said, the implicit message of all of this is, you know,
Aristotle conquered the entire world, the sense of his sort of vaunting
ambition, and the sages sort of giving him a counterpoint to those
things. What it really means to be strong, what it really means
to be wise and so on. Let's now continue the story. So
bottom of ל"ב עמוד א'. אמר להו, Amar Lehu, he said to
them, the ten lines from the bottom, he said to them, בעינא
דאזילנא למדינת אפריקי, Ba'ina De'azalna Lemdinat Afriki, I want to go to
Africa. אמרו ליה, Amru Lei, they said to him, לא מציית אזלת,
Lo Matzyat Azlat, no, you can't go to Africa. דפסיקי הרי חושך,
Difsikei Harei Choshech, the mountains of darkness are between you and Africa.
Sounds like more like Middle Earth. I know. אמר להו, Amar Lehu,
he said, לא סגי דלא אזלנא, Lo Sagi Delo Azalna, no, I'm
sorry, I'm going, it will not suffice, it will not not to
go, I must go. אמרו ליה, Amru Lei, and because of that,
אימתו הכי משאלינא לך, Eimtu Hachi Mishailina Lach, I'm asking you how
to go there, what's the best way to do it? I not
asking you whether I should, I'm asking you how. אלא מאי עביד,
Ella Mai Avid, what can I do to get there? אמרו ליה,
Amru Lei, אייתי חמרי לוביא, Aisi Chamrei Liva'ei, get Libyan donkeys, דפרשי
בחברא, De'parshi Be'chavra, that move, some say this means move in the
darkness, because they have to get through the mountains of darkness, some
say it means it moves by your words, you know, so it
follows your voice, ואייתי כיבורי דמתני, Ve'aisi Kivorei De'masni, take coils of
rope, דקטרא בהאי גיסא, De'katra Be'hai Gisa, tie it up at one
end, דכי אתית, De'ki Asis, that when you come, נגדית בגווייהו, Nagdis
Be'gavaihu, you'll be able to hold onto it, ואתית לאתראך, Ve'asis Le'asrach,
and you'll come to your place. I don't exactly get what that
means. I mean, I assume if you can throw a rope to
the other side, actually, maybe it means that, have the donkey have
one end of the rope on the donkey, the donkey will find
its way through, and then you follow the, you know, the rope,
you know, if you held out the other end of the rope.
I know and tie this and when you go back, you'll just,
okay, but that assumes that I know how to get there. The
problem is coming back, right? That some want to say that, that
that'll help you get back, but how do you get there in
the first place? Maybe you're on the donkeys. Why not use the
donkeys on the return trip? I thought it was more like, you
know, you throw your rope, maybe the donkey carries
the rope, you know,
one end of the rope, and the donkey knows its way through
and then you sort of go follow the rope through. Anyway, that's
the answer they gave him. What, do you think there's like no
light in Africa? I have no idea. No, just the mountains, the
way to get there. The Africa, no, but the mountains are, mountains
are darkness. Okay, now, עביד הכי, Abid Hachi, he did that, ואזל
מטא להו למחוזא, Ve'azal Mato Lehu Lemachoza, he came to a city,
דכולהו נשי, De'kulhu Neshei, which was all women. Amazon. The Amazons. Now,
I looked up, all this was a fun little exercise at night,
Amazons according to mythology, there's a question where they lived, but many
according to many myths they lived in Africa, they lived in Libya,
Libya was actually the name of the entire African continent and we
just mentioned the Libyan donkeys and so on. So he went and
got his donkeys. So he went to, yeah, oh, maybe that's actually
the פשט, Pshat, I didn't put the two together, but maybe that's
like a homing donkey, like a homing pigeon, maybe that's why it's
Libyan, they'll find their way back, so that would reinforce my read
of that about with the rope. Anyway, he came to a city
which were all women and there are myths of Alexander and the
Amazons. Okay, there are myths about this. I'm not, not this story,
but general about this an encounter with the Amazons. בעי למעבד קרבא
בהדייהו, Ba'ei Lemevid Karva Be'hadaihu, he wanted to wage war against them,
he's waging war against everybody, he's Alexander. אמרו ליה, Amru Lei, they
said to him, the women, the women, אי קטלת לן, Ei Katlas
Lan, look, it's a no-win situation, if you are victorious and you
kill us and win the war, יאמרו נשי קטלי, Yameru Neshei Katlei,
people will say you killed women, so you don't want that on
your record. אי קטלינא לך, Ei Katlina Lach, and if we kill
you. even worse for you. יאמרו מלכא דקטלוהו נשי, yamru malka de-katluhu
nashi, the king that was killed by women. So you know what?
It doesn't do you any good to go to war with us.
So אמר להן, amar lahen, okay, so apparently he said, you're right,
forget it, I won't go to war. Okay. אמר להן, amar lahen,
I don't know if there's a subtext here about men always looking
for war and women trying to find ways of peace, but whatever.
אמר Amar, להן, he said to them, אייתו לי נהמא, aisu li
nahama, bring me bread. אייתו ליה נהמא דדהבא, aisu lei nahama de-dahava,
they brought him gold bread made out of gold, אפתורא דדהבא, a-patura
de-dahava, on a gold table. So אמר להו, amar lehu, he said
to them, מי אכלי אינשי נהמא דדהבא, mi achli inshi nahama de-dahava,
how am I supposed to eat gold bread? אמרו ליה, amru lei,
they said to him, אלא אי נהמא בעית, ela ei nahama bayat,
if you wanted bread, לא הוה לך באתרך נהמא למיכל? lo hava
lach be-atrach nahama le-meichal? If you wanted bread, you could have eaten
bread back at home. Why did you leave home למישקל מסא סוכל
le-mishkal masa suchel that you came here? Now it seems here the
message again is, and this is pointed out to us here, take
a look back at your Jewish Encyclopedia, okay. He says on the
flip side here, the gold bread, the gold bread. This is on
the flip side as an answer he says, and they quote it.
This satire on the ambition of conquerors recurs frequently in Jewish legends.
It does not appear in whatever, but it's found in Plutarch's essay
on the virtuous deeds of women. Pytheas, a rich Greek in the
time of Xerxes who forced his fellow citizens to work for him
in a gold mine, is served by his wife, again so it's
the woman, with gold bread to demonstrate the absurdity of his greed.
This moral is connected with Alexander in another form, okay, etc. So
the point being, and this goes back to the point, right? You
know, if you want, be satisfied with simple bread. Stay at home.
Don't go overseas. You know, איזהו עשיר השמח בחלקו. eizehu ashir ha-sameiach
be-chelko. If you're going because you want gold and you want this,
what can you eat? Can you eat the gold? Right? So what's
the point? Stay at home where things where you'll have the bread
that you need and you don't have to you know have this
type of greed and ambition that's leading you to these faraway places
for more and more gold. Okay, now כי נפיק ואתי, ki nafik
ve-ati, when he came out of the city, כתיב אבבא דמחוזא, ketiv
a-bava de-machoza, he wrote on the gates of the city, אנא אלכסנדרוס
מוקדון, ana Alexandrus Mokdon, I Alexander of Macedon, הוינא שטיא, havaeina shatya,
I was a fool, עד דאתיתי למדינת אפריקי דנשי, ad de-asisi li-medinat
Afriki de-nashi, until I came to the country of Africa of women,
the Amazon presumably, וילפית עצה מנשי, ve-yalfit eiza min nashi, and I
learned advice from women. Okay, so that's what he wrote. So you
know maybe what this, by the way, if I'm right that the
story with the ten sages and with the Amazons, or certainly that's
what the Jewish Encyclopedia says, is the same message about not being
overarching in your greed, it's interesting because who taught him the lesson
better? The women! Not the sages! They had answers, but he was
coming from a different philosophy, he didn't listen to the answers. They
maybe made it you know very like very concrete, you know, and
they brought it home. He really learned this, it wasn't just some
intellectual exchange. I don't know, but it's quite fascinating, right? It's quite
fascinating that they're having like a little battle of wits, but he
only admits defeat, he admits that he's learned something, he's changed his
perspective you know through you know through this encounter with the women.
So it's fascinating to put the two side by side. What does
that say about the transmission? Do they just take this block of
text that traveled around together right despite the fact that it makes
the rabbis look like secondary to the women, not what they usually
want? No, that's what I'm saying. So is it a literary thing
they break up the text or you know do they think about
it or they just threw it in? That much of took these
stories and threw it in. Yeah, it's a good question. I really
don't know and if you know you read from this thing it
seems that these were different that definitely in sort of classical literature
they were different units and in our גמרא they're all stitched together
as one big unit. Right, so I understand obviously, but that goes
to your question of were these initially taught together or were they
separate units. Right, but now that they're being put together it does
create that context. But the other point could be that maybe you
know maybe the story with the sages it's more important to show
that the sages would win an intellectual battle of wits to show
the wisdom of the sages over the wisdom of Alexander whereas by
this story it's like it's the education of of of Alexander so
you know as opposed to they did better it's what's what are
your goals? Are your goals to give Alexander a different perspective, to
educate him, or your goals to you know win a battle of
wits to show who's smarter? There's no reason to think they did
better, they said the sages beat us, right, which could be that
they and actually part of the point is that the women had
both because they actually also won the battle of wits, they showed
who was smarter because if you're teaching somebody and they're changing their
perspective, so it is a very good question, it is you know
when you juxtapose them, the women get certainly get the better of
Alexander. Alexander more than the sages. Okay, so now it continues: כי
שקיל ואתי, Ki shakil ve'ati, as he was going and coming. But
you'll see at the end, the sages have the last word. So,
כי שקיל ואתי Ki shakil ve'ati when he was going, he left
the city, he was going in his various travels in Africa. Alexander
did go to Africa, obviously first of all he conquered Egypt, which
is how you get Alexandria, but he even went further and he
did do some forays into like Libya and so on and he
crossed the Sahara, parts of the Sahara. So all of this I
know from checking it up last time. Anyway, so כי שקיל ואתי
יתיב אההוא מאינא, Ki shakil ve'ati yatib ahahu mayina, so he sat
by a well. כאכל נהמא, Ka'akhal nahama, he was eating bread, he
had to wash his hands. הוי בידיה כוורי דמלחא, Havei bideih kavrei
de'milkha, he had some salty fish. בהדי דמחוורי להו, Bahadi demakhvrei lehu,
he was rinsing them in the well water. נפל בהו ריחא, Nafal
behu reykha, a beautiful smell came from them. Some say רוחא rukha
that they became, they rejuvenated, they came back to life. אמר, he
said, שמע מינה האי עינא מגן עדן אתי. Shema mina hai eina
mi'gan eden ati. Oh, this must be, he found the fountain of
youth, right? The גן עדן. Gan Eden. So which is fascinating because
of course, you know, it seems that the Garden, that the גן
עדן, Gan Eden, which is by the Tigris and the Euphrates in
בראשית, Bereishit, it was somewhere in like the Fertile Crescent area. Here
it's in Africa, but okay. He found the wellspring of the Garden
of Eden. מגן עדן אתי. Mi'gan eden ati. איכא דאמרי שקא מהני
מיה, Ika de'amri shaka mehani maya, some say he took that water,
טרא באפיה, tara be'apeih, he washed his face with it and maybe
somehow he realized that that was גן עדן Gan Eden water. איכא
דאמרי אמדלי כולי אדמתא—no, Ika de'amri amdali kulei admata no, maybe not.
I'm sorry. After he realized, maybe not how he realized, after he
realized, what do you do to take advantage of this water from
גן עדן? Gan Eden? So one says he washed his face with
it. Maybe he thought it would have some good benefit, invigorating. Good
point, good work. Okay, another version is, איכא דאמרי אדלי כולי, Ika
de'amri adli kulei, he followed the whole stream, עד דמטא לפתחא דגן
עדן, Ad demata le'pitkha de'gan eden, till he came to the opening
of גן עדן. Gan Eden. Maybe that brought him back to the
Fertile Crescent. Who knows where it started. רמא קלא, Rama kala, he
yelled, פתחו לי בבא, Pitkhu li bava, open up for me the
gate. I want to go into גן עדן. Gan Eden. אמרו ליה,
Amru leih, they said to him, זה השער לה', Ze hashayar l'Hashem,
of course it says וכו' vechu very judiciously cut off, צדיקים יבאו
בו. Tzadikim
yavo'u vo. Excuse me, this is only for the righteous, which ultimately
is the message of the battle with the ten sages, right? You
think what it means to accomplish is to conquer worlds? No, it's
to be righteous. That's who gets into גן עדן. Gan Eden. You
don't get into גן עדן. Gan Eden. So, אמר להון, Amar lehon,
look, אנא נמי מלכא, Ana nami malka, I'm not going to argue
that I'm righteous but I'm a king, אנא, ana, אנא מלכא אנא.
ana malka ana. חשיב חשיבינא, Khashiv khashivina, I'm a person of significance.
הבו לי מידי, Havu li midi, at least give me something from
גן עדן. Gan Eden. So יהבו ליה, Yahavu leih, they, whoever the
they is, the anonymous they gave him, גולגלתא, gulgata, like a sphere
or an eyeball, חדא, khada, one, one eyeball. אתייא, Atya, he took
it, תקליה לכולי דהבא וכספא דידיה. Taklei l'khulei de'hava ve'kaspa dideih. Now
this is pretty obvious what the message is. He took all of
his gold and silver and weighed it against the eyeball, בהדי, bahadi,
לא הוה מתקלא, lo hava matkala, and it wouldn't counterbalance. The eyeball
was heavier. So אמר להון לרבנן, Amar lehon l'rabanan, now he came
back to the sages, the רבנן, rabanan, presumably that's the same as
the זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, doesn't matter, it's a different appellation but
clearly it's Jewish wisdom. He came to the rabbis, he said מאי
האי? Mai hai? What's going on with this? Why does it weigh
so much more than everything I have? אמרי, Amri, they said, גולגלתא
דעינא דבישרא ודמא. Gulgata de'eina de'bisra ve'dama. This is an eye of
flesh and blood. So דלא כשבע, De'lo kasava, it never will be
satisfied. So, you know, so therefore it weighs more. You can have
all the gold and silver in the world and it's not as
much as you will desire. Your desire can always exceed, right? אוהב
כסף לא ישבע כסף. Ohev kesef lo yisba kesef. Your desire will
always exceed what you're able to achieve and to conquer. So, yes.
Language training more towards a colloquial Aramaic? Yeah, that's a good question.
It is tacked on. I'm wondering about that. It does, you know,
if the grammar here is shifting. It does seem that a little
bit, I'm not expert enough to say that, but right, that goes
back to Rivka's question. Maybe this last piece, you know, was a
later piece or a different piece. I was wondering that but the
way they're all put together creates a nice balance. You have the
Amazons in the middle, you have the rabbis or the sages winning
a battle of wits but not actually being victorious and now you
have the sages again and it's the same message, right? No matter,
right, he wants to get into גן עדן. Gan Eden. The message
is I'm sorry, you think you're great, it's part of your name,
but it's your last name, but it doesn't count for anything when
it comes to the Garden of Eden. You should have listened to
those sages, right? You should have known what real greatness is about
and then the message he gets is here's an eye, and that's
the same message. All your gold and silver will never make you
happy anyway. Okay, so אמר להו Amar lehu ממאי דהכי הוא? Mimai
de'hakhi hu? How do you know that's what it really is? How
do I, can I trust you? So they said the following. שקלי
קלילי דעפרא Shakli Kalili De'afra take a little dirt וכסיה Vechasye and
cover it. לאלתר Le'altar so he did that, תקלא Takla and immediately
it weighed, meaning it counterbalanced, it wasn't so heavy. Now what's the
symbol of the dirt? So you could just say he was blinding
the eye. Yes, immediately it occurred to me and the רש''י Rashi
says this, when somebody dies, you put dirt on their, you know,
on their body and on their eye, first thing you do is
you close their eyes. So basically it's saying look, you'll see what
happens, you know, once death occurs and we're all going to die,
right? So that's also part of the message here then, you know,
then no longer, you know, all your ambitions and desires go away.
All right, so דכתיב Dechtiv and the verse says שאול ואבדון לא
תשבענה, Sheol Ve'avadon Lo Tisbe'enah, you know, the שאול Sheol and the
destruction will never be satisfied. And the end of the פסוק is,
it's quoted in the מפרש mefareish here, it says similarly the eyes
of a human will never be satisfied, ועיני אדם לא תשבענה Ve'einei
Adam Lo Tisbe'enah is the end of the פסוק. Okay, but also
obviously the association with death and the שאול, Sheol, the underworld, is
also about, you know, about living a virtuous life as opposed to
a life of wealth and of amassing wealth. תנא דבי אליהו, Tana
Debei Eliyahu, we taught from the school of אליהו, Eliyahu, גיהנום למעלה
מן הרקיע. Gehenom Lema'ala Min Harakia. ויש אומרים, Veyeish Omrim, since we're
talking about גיהנום, Gehenom, גיהנום Gehenom is above the heavens. This is
like metaphorically or they actually think this is? I don't know what
that means at all, but ויש אומרים לאחורי הרי חושך, Veyeish Omrim
Leachorei Harei Choshech, I have no idea what that means. It's also
very like funny because we always think about heaven being above, right?
What does that mean למעלה מן הרקיע? Lema'ala Min Harakia? It also
evokes the earlier part of the discussion about, you know, about heaven
and earth, east and west. Some say above the רקיע, some say
behind the רקיע. I have nothing of insight to say about this,
about this line. I don't know what, you know, what sort of,
what this is supposed to signify. ויש אומרים לאחורי, Veyeish Omrim Leachorei,
excuse me, לאחורי הרי חושך, Leachorei Harei Choshech, behind the mountains of
darkness. So it's on this earth, it's behind the mountains of darkness
which is also where Alexander went. But what's interesting? So it says
גיהנום. Gehenom. Okay, גיהנום, Gehenom, hell, is it above the heavens or
is it behind the mountains of darkness? You know, so I have
no idea what that is supposed to mean. I mean, maybe just
now I'm speculating that it could mean that there are two ways
of sinning: one way is depravity which is like behind the mountains
of darkness going into darkness, and the other way of sinning is
maybe the sort of Alexander way, you know, it's not necessarily that
you're depraved and you're murdering, but it's about your ambition which exceeds
the heavens and your lusts and your desires which are not necessarily
about depravity. So maybe that's sort of ties in here. Of course
you don't want this to be too negative to Alexander because as
was pointed out, he had a very positive relationship with the Jews,
he was very good to the Jews, he never was, he wasn't
a bad king, okay, but you know, they did have these myths
that they were and obviously the myth of Alexander and the sages,
it's good to appropriate that myth and have it be about our
sages and them maybe trying to teach him a lesson like the
Amazons. So in the end though, you know, it does seem like
they get this last word and maybe, but in the end, even
with this whole thing and he sort of was picking up the
vibes in terms of not getting into the Garden of Eden, he
only admitted defeat to the Amazons still, right, he only admitted defeat
to the women. Okay, now the גמרא ends, תנא רבי חייא, Tana
Rabbi Chiyya, we taught Rabbi Chiyya, it's not exactly clear what how
this connects to the previous thing. כל העוסק בתורה בלילה. Kol Ha'osek
BaTorah Balaila. Because of the חושך, choshech, darkness? I guess, yeah, darkness,
maybe, yeah. Anybody who learns Torah at night, שכינה כנגדו, Shechinah Kenegdo,
has the שכינה Shechinah opposite him. שנאמר, קומי רוני בלילה לראש אשמורות,
Kumi Roni Balaila Lerosh Ashmurot, get up and sing at night, so
it's a whole Rav Soloveitchik has a beautiful sort of essay about
the Torah as a form of שירה, shira, as singing and joy,
at the top of the watches, the watches were in the night
like the night was divided into watches. שפכי כמים לבך נוכח פני
ה', Shifchi Chamayim Libech Noach Pnei Hashem, pour out your heart like
water in front of the presence of God. So part of what
this might be saying is, you know, there's a number of things
like in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot about כל הלומד תורה בלילה Kol
Halomed Torah Balaila and so on, you know, is because if you
don't have electric lights, right, it's very dark, it's a time that
actually everybody used the night as the opportunity to sleep, you know,
they didn't have the idea, they were much more linked to the
sun, they didn't have this idea of like artificial rhythms, I mean
their body rhythms were much more linked. So it was a big
thing to learn at night, but also because you're, you know, extending
yourself beyond your normal waking hours, but also it was a time
when maybe, you know why שכינה Shechinah was כנגדו? kenegdo? For the
מזיקין? mazikin? No, I would say, I would say because nobody else
was there, meaning it's just you and God, it's just you and
the Torah, you know, you don't have other people around, you don't
even have the social aspects of learning, you don't have the בית
מדרש, Beit Medrash, you don't have the חברותא. chavruta. So that can
be a very special like spiritual time. So that's how I read
it is like, you know, is that you're just there with God.
אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Amar Rabbi Elazar Ben Azaryah, so said
Rabbi Elazar Ben Azaryah, תלמידי חכמים מרבים שלום בעולם. Talmidei Chachamim Marbim
Shalom Ba'olam. People know this, I don't know, it's we're talking about
Torah, right, and we're talking maybe about because the sages beat out
Alexander the Alexander and forcing peace, it's through learning תורה *Torah*. Is
that what you were saying, Dov? Okay. So שנאמר *shene'emar* וכל בניך
למודי השם *v'chol banayich limudei Hashem* all of your children are learning
from are those you know learned it from God ורב שלום בניך
*v'rav shalom banayich* great peace is your sons. Now you'll notice what
doesn't it have? It doesn't have אל תקרי בניך אלא בוניך *al
tikrei banayich ela bonayich* the normal way some people add that in.
But a normal way that this מדרש *Midrash* ends is don't read
your sons but your builders. And your builders are those who build
תורה *Torah*. But you know there's a lot of literature around that
אל תקרי *al tikrei* because why does בוניך *bonayich* mean more תורה
*Torah* scape says than בניך *banayich*? I mean first of all it
says למודי השם *limudei Hashem* so it talks already about learning. And
children like we speak very much about the idea that like you
know if you teach תורה *Torah* to somebody it's like you gave
birth to them. So why would you need the אל תקרי *al
tikrei*? So it's interesting that sometimes it doesn't have the אל תקרי
*al tikrei* and it could be the אל תקרי *al tikrei* was
added on later that actually it just ends right here with the
part of the פסוק *pasuk*. Okay and then now the reason also
we ended with this I don't know the reason we ended with
אגדתא *Agadata* but the reason we I would suggest the reason we
switched to some nice little אגדתא *Agadata* about learning תורה *Torah* is
this is the last גמרא *Gemara* that we're going to learn. Meaning
of קדשים *Kodshim*. From here on in it's all משניות *Mishnayos*. Now
thing is though that's the way the וילנא ש"ס *Vilna Shas* organized
it. The real no that's not true because קנים *Kinnim* comes at
the end but קנים *Kinnim* is all משנה *Mishnah*. So this really
is the last גמרא *Gemara* that exists in מסכת קדשים *Masechet Kodshim*.
So the idea as גמרא *Gemara* often ends with more מדרש *Midrash*
and ending with sort of the value of תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*
you know is sort of how this ends. So הדרן עלך היו
קופצים *Hadran Alach Hayu Koftzim* so with that we end that fourth
פרק *perek* and we end the גמרא *Gemara* of סדר קדשים *Seder
Kodshim* and now we just have משניות *Mishnayos* to learn for the
next few days. So let's just read Joe you're always ready to
go we have another two minutes. So we're going to start the
next פרק *perek*. Okay so that was all a lovely digression but
ultimately what did they do they had dismembered the animal. Remember that
they had dismembered the animal and they brought it up to halfway
on the ramp. Now אמר להם הממונה *Amar lahem hamemuneh* the appointed
person the you know whoever was sort of the the one who
oversaw the division of responsibilities and the and the lottery he said
to them ברכו ברכה bracha אחת *barchu bracha achat* make a blessing.
Now so if oh because the other thing ended I'm sorry it
ended by saying after they dismembered it and put it on the
ramp they went to the לשכת הגזית *Lishkat HaGazit* to דאוון *davven*.
To no to say קריאת שמע *Kriyat Shema*. Oh to say קריאת
שמע *Kriyat Shema* because here they're going to talk about קריאת שמע
*Kriyat Shema*. Okay? Okay you might be right you usually are. בואו
לזמן *Bo'u l'zman* yeah you're right it said for קריאת שמע *Kriyat
Shema*. So then they would they said make one ברכה *bracha*. So
which ברכה *bracha* did they make? So they did a shortened דאוון
*davven* because they didn't have the time they had to get back
to their קרבנות korbanos. *korbanos*. There's a lot of discussion over in
ברכות *Berachot* about like people that teach תורה *Torah* don't have time
to do a full דאוון *davven* and so on. So they did
a short דאוון *davven*. They did not say the ברכה *bracha* it's
a debate in the גמרא *Gemara* in ברכות *Berachot* but the the
best sort of the more satisfying answer is they did not say
יוצר המאורות *Yotzer HaMe'orot* because it was not yet הנץ החמה *hanetz
hachama*. It was only after עלות השחר *alot hashachar*. So they said
only the ברכה *bracha* of בוחר בעמו ישראל באהבה *bocher b'amo Yisrael
b'ahava*. So make one blessing. Did they just say that or the
whole אהבה רבה *Ahava Rabba*? I'm not sure. והן ברכו *V'hen barchu*
they made the ברכה *bracha*, קראו עשרת הדברות *kar'u aseret hadibrot* and
then they read the עשרת הדברות *aseret hadibrot* before doing שמע *Shema*
and שמע והיה אם שמוע ויאמר *Shema, V'haya Im Shamoa, Vayomer* the
three פרשיות *parshiyot* of שמע *Shema*. The גמרא *Gemara* in ברכות *Berachot*
says that they wanted to say the עשרת הדברות *aseret hadibrot* for
everybody have that a staple of the דאוון *davven* but they didn't
because people would say the מינים *minim* which is the Jewish sectarians
would say or maybe it means the Jewish Christians would say that
this is the this is the real תורה *Torah* is just the
ten commandments you don't have to worry about the rest. So even
though there was a idea of focusing on that because it certainly
was a way of encapsulating the you know a lot of the
מצוות *mitzvot* but neverth- so they had it here in the בית
המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* they did not make this a standard part of
liturgy then they had the three parts of שמע *Shema* then העבודה
*Ha'Avodah* I'm sorry העבודה *Ha'Avodah*. Now what did they say in I'm
sorry ויאמר *Vayomer* where am I שמע והיה אם שמוע ויאמר *Shema,
V'haya Im Shamoa, Vayomer*. Now ברכו את העם שלש ברכות *Barchu et
ha'am shalosh brachot* they blessed the people three blessings. Now a lot
of people take out the words they blessed the people because they're
just doing their own דאוון *davven*. So they said three blessings. What
three blessings did they say? אמת ויציב *Emet V'Yatziv* which ends with
גואל ישראל *Go'el Yisrael* so the blessing after שמע *Shema* והעבודה *v'ha'avodah*.
Now the עבודה avodah, *avodah* is רצה *retzei*. What ברכה *bracha* do
we say when we say רצה *retzei*? המחזיר שכינתו לציון *ha'machazir shechinato
l'tziyon*. They were not saying that. So some say they ended a
ברכה *bracha* which basically says that you should accept our sacrifices ברצון
*b'ratzon* or some say it's the ברכה *bracha* we say when we
do ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim. *birkat kohanim* which we say to end
רצה *retzei* which is שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד *she'otcha levadecha b'yira na'avod*.
Okay but something about the sacrificial worship they're about to do וברכת
כהנים Kohanim *u'birkat kohanim*. Now this ברכת כהנים *birkat kohanim* was not
the נשיאת כפים *nesiat kapayim* that we do in public with the
people so this was just the ברכה *bracha* of some say it
was a ברכה *bracha* for God to say bless us that we
should like you know that you have blessed us to be blessed.
your people, like the ברכה that they say before ברכת כהנים. Or
some say they recited the פסוקים, psukim, but they didn't do נשיאת
כפיים. nesias kapayim. Okay, so either a blessing for their role in
נשיאת כפיים nesias kapayim or they said it without actually doing it
to the people. ובשבת מוסיפים ברכה אחת למשמר היוצא. U'v'Shabbos mosifim bracha
achas l'mishmar hayotzei. And on Shabbos, the departing group of כהנים would
give a blessing to those coming in. And the blessing would be,
it would be more like what we call a blessing, not a
ברוך אתה. Baruch Atah. They said מי ששכן שמו בבית הזה הוא
יתן ביניכם אהבה ואחוה שלום וריעות. Mi sheshachan shemo babayis hazeh, hu
yitein beineichem ahavah v'achvah, shalom v'reiyus. Very beautiful. Right? God whose presence
is in this house to give amongst you brotherhood and peace and
loving-kindness and so on. So they gave them that blessing of unity,
which is interesting. Why? Maybe there was competition of who gets to
do which things, but anyway, a very beautiful, a very beautiful blessing.
We will pick up with this tomorrow and I want to again
iterate, reiterate the idea of the relationship of תפילה tefillah to the
קרבנות. korbanos And here they're making, doing a תפילה tefillah before the
קרבנות framing the קרבן korban with a ברכה for the עבודה, importance
in thinking about the relationship of the.